A Finding Aid to the Robert Aitken Papers, circa 1900-1960, in the Archives of American Art AAA.aitkrobe
Archives of American Art
Robert Aitken papers
circa 1900-1960
AAA.aitkrobe
Archives of American Art
0.5 Linear feet
The papers of California-born sculptor Robert Aitken measure 0.5 linear feet and date from circa 1900-1960. The collection primarily consists of photographs of Aitken in his studio and photographs of his sculpture including fountain figures, mausouleum doors, medallions, refliefs, and portrait busts. Also found is a photograph of Theodore Roosevelt at the dedication of the Navy Monument in Union Square, San Francisco, in 1902. The collection also includes one 1904 letter from Benjamin Wheeler to Robert Aitken thanking Aitken for a bust of George Washington, and scattered clippings and postcards reproducing works of art by Aitken.
Aitken, Robert, 1878-1949
Scope and Contents note
The papers of California-born sculptor Robert Aitken measure 0.5 linear feet and date from circa 1900-1960. The collection primarily consists of photographs of Aitken in his studio and photographs of his sculpture including fountain figures, mausoleum doors, medallions, reliefs, and portrait busts. Also found is a photograph of Theodore Roosevelt at the dedication of the Navy Monument in Union Square, San Francisco, in 1902. The collection also includes one 1904 letter from Benjamin Wheeler to Robert Aitken thanking Aitken for a bust of George Washington, and scattered clippings and postcards reproducing works of art by Aitken.
Some of the photographs are silver gelatin and gold toned silver gelatin prints, and some were taken by noted photographer De Witt Ward.
Arrangement note
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Series 1: Robert Aitken Papers, circa 1900-1960
Biographical/Historical note
Noted sculptor Robert Aitken (1878-1949) was born in San Francisco, California, and taught at the Mark Hopkins Institute of Art from 1901-1904. He studied in Paris in 1897 and from 1904-1907, and then settled in New York City where he spent most of his career teaching at the National Academy of Design.
He completed numerous sculpture commissions including portrait busts, medallions and coins, reliefs, and fountain figures. His works include the "Fountain of Earth" for San Francisco's Panama Pacific Exposition, the Navy Monument in San Francisco's Union Square, doors for the Greenhut and John W. Gates Mausoleums in New York, several military sculptures at West Point, and Guardian Figures at the National Archives building and the West Pediment of the United States Supreme Court building, both in Washington D. C.
Aitken was a member of the National Academy of Design, the National Arts Club, the National Institute of Arts and Letters, the National Sculpture Society and the New York Architectural League.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original materials requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D. C. Research Center.
Existence and Location of Copies note
This collection is also available on 35 mm microfilm reel 1027. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the collection as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated to the Archives of American Art by the Cooper-Hewitt Museum in November 1973.
Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Ward, De Witt; Wheeler, Benjamin; Artists' studios--Photographs; Monuments--California--San Francisco; Monuments--Washington (D.C.); Photographs; Sculptors
- Robert Aitken Papers, circa 1900-1960; Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1, OV 2
  - Letter, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    - Aitken and Busts, circa 1900-circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aitken and "Fountain of the Earth" Statue, Panama Pacific Exposition, circa 1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes blank postcards of the fountain
    - Aitken and Friezes, circa 1900-circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Aitken and Military Sculpture, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Aitken and Monmument to American Navy in Union Square, circa 1902 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Oversized material housed in OV 2.
    - Aitken and National Academy of Design Medallion, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Aitken and Samuel Gompers Monument, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Oversized material housed in OV 2
    - Book Ends, circa 1900-circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Busts, circa 1900-circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - Frederick W. Schumacher Frieze, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Mausoleum Doors, circa 1900-circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Medallions, circa 1900-circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Monuments, circa 1900-circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - National Archives Figures, circa 1930s; circa 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Includes 3 news clippings circa 1959-1960
    - Other Sculpture, circa 1900-circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    - Unidentified Individuals in a Forest, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Oversized Aitken and Monument to American Navy in Union Square from Box 1, Folder 6 (Box OV 2)
    - Oversized Aitken and Samuel Gompers Monument from Box 1, Folder 8 (Box OV 2)